<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//KDE//DTD DocBook XML V4.2-Based Variant V1.1//EN" "/usr/share/sgml/docbook/xml-dtd-4.2-1.0-17.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
	
	<articleinfo>
		<title>SpanLib - Spectral Analysis Library</title>
	</articleinfo>

	<!--#################################################################-->
	<sect1>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			This package provides a F90 module containg a minmal collection of subroutine to perform
			<emphasis>Principal Componant Analysis</emphasis> (PCA),
			<emphasis>Multi-channel Singular Spectrum Analysis</emphasis> (MSSA), reconstruction
			of components and phase composites.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			<emphasis>PCA</emphasis> is also know as Empirical Orthogonal Functions (EOFs) decomposition:
			it decomposes a space-time signal in pairs of spatial EOFs and temporal PCs
			that are the eigen solutions of the covariance (or correlation) matrix of the initial signal.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			<emphasis>MSSA</emphasis> works in the same way except that EOF are spatio-temporal, and that the diagonalized
			matrix is built not only using covariances (or correlations) between spatial points,
			but also lag covariances.
			Therefore, MSSA is particularly efficient to remove white noise, and extract oscillations and nonlinear
			trends, even on short sample.
			It uses a window parameter that corresponds to the maximal lag for lag correlations.
			Oscillations with a period lower than this window can be typically extracted by MSSA.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			The package also provides the possibility to <emphasis>reconstruct part of the signal</emphasis>
			due to selected modes, for both PCA and MSSA.
			Finally, <emphasis>oscillations</emphasis> extracted by MSSA and reconstructed can be reorganized
			in <emphasis>phases composites</emphasis>: the oscillations are presented over their averaged cycle,
			decomposed in a fixed number of phases
			(like one can do for the annual cycle over 12 months for example).
		</para>
			
		<para>
				More information about PCA and MSSA may be found in papers and on the web.
				See for example:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>MSSA: <link linkend="#plva94">Plaut and Vautard, 1994</link>.</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
	</sect1>

	<!--#################################################################-->
	<sect1>
		<title>F90 subroutines</title>

		<MY_SUBROUTINES />
		
	</sect1>

	<!--#################################################################-->
	<sect1>
		<title>Examples</title>
		
		<sect2>
			<title>A pure Fortran 90 example</title>
			
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>A example using the Python interface</title>

		</sect2>

	</sect1>

	<!--#################################################################-->
	<sect1>
		<title>References</title>
		<anchor id="#plva94" />
	</sect1>

	Documentation generated by perl and xslproc
	
</article>